Guide to the Bedinger and Dandridge Family Papers, 1752-2000
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
Bedinger and Dandridge Family papers 1752-2000
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Bedinger family.
30 Linear Feet 13,000 Items
Bedinger and Dandridge families of Virginia, West Virginia, Kentucky, Ohio, and New York.
Collection consist of journals, correspondence, poems, reviews, and other papers of the Bedinger, Dandridge, Washington, Henry Clay, and Adam Stephen families, of Virginia, Kentucky, and Ohio; and of the Cornwall, Lawrence, Mitchell, Walter Bowne, and Rufus King Southgate families, of Connecticut, Maine, and New York primarily created or collected by Caroline Danske (Bedinger) Dandridge. The papers fall into six classes: journals and fragments of journals of Danske Dandridge (1864-1909), Henry Bedinger (1830s), and Daniel Bedinger (1811); correspondence and material on Kentucky and the northern Shenandoah Valley during the Revolutionary period; family correspondence, genealogies, and memoirs used in writing the Bedinger family history; papers of Henry Bedinger, the American Minister to Denmark in the 1850s; poems, reviews and literary correspondence of Danske Dandridge, and poems and prose of her father, Henry Dandridge, and of her daughter, Serena Catherine Dandridge; and horticultural writings of Danske Dandridge.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Bedinger-Dandridge Papers were acquired by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library from 1955 to 1959, and 2003.
Biographical Note
Bedinger and Dandridge families of Virginia, West Virginia, Kentucky, Ohio, and New York.
Collection Overview
Collection includes the correspondence and papers of five generations of families from Virginia, West Virginia, Kentucky, Ohio, and New York chiefly created or collected by Carolina Danske (Bedinger) Dandridge. The primary portion of the collection is made up of the personal and family papers of Danske Dandridge (1858-1914), a writer and horticulturist. From 1866 to her marriage in 1877, Danske Dandridge's correspondence is concerned with social life in Virginia and Washington, D.C., and with family matters. Her literary correspondence begins in the early 1880s and continues until the year of her death. Correspondents include John Esten Cooke, Edmund C. Stedman, Oliver Wendell Holmes, John Greenleaf Whittier, and Thomas W. Higginson. There are sustained exchanges of letters with William Hayes Ward, editor of The Brooklyn Independent which published much of her work; with the poet Lizette Woodworth Reese of Baltimore; and Margaretta Lippincott. Material on gardening begins to appear in the papers for the 1890s and includes a large number of letters and eleven notebooks.
Danske Dandridge's family correspondence continues with here sister Mrs. J. F. B. (Mary Bedinger) Mitchell, and her brother, Henry Bedinger IV, as well as with her numerous cousins.
Correspondence of Adam Stephen Dandridge (1844-1924) reflects his career in the West Virginia House of Representatives and his business as a seller of farm machinery.
Correspondence and papers of Serena Katherine (Violet) Dandridge, daughter of Danske and Adam Stephen Dandridge, bear on her career as an illustrator for the zoologist Hubert Lyman Clark, and reflect her interest in women's suffrage and the Swedenborgian Church. There are also twelve volumes of her writings in manuscript.
Correspondence and papers of Danske Dandridge's father, Henry Bedinger Dandridge III, include letters on literary subjects from Thomas Willis White, Philip Pendleton Cooke, and Nathaniel Beverly Tucker; papers from his years as a member of the United States House of Representatives from 1845 to 1849; records of his service, 1853-1858, first as a consul and then as minister of the United States in Sweden and in particular his negotiation of the treaty with Sweden in 1857; and his notebooks containing poems and comments on social life in Virginia.
Letters of Caroline B. (Lawrence) Bedinger, mother of Danske Dandridge, to her husband's family in the South and her relatives in New York concern her experience as a young woman in Washington, D.C., and Virginia; her stay in Copenhagen; the Civil War experiences of her husband's family and her own; family life; and the education of her children.
The collection contains a large number of transcripts made by Danske Dandridge from originals in the possession of various branches of her family, including the Swearingens, Shepherds, Morgans, Rutherfords, Worthingtons, Washingtons, Kings, Brownes, and Lawrences for the period from the American Revolution to the Civil War. There are also copies of letters and documents from the Lyman C. Draper manuscripts at the University of Wisconsin. Essentially, they are the papers of three brothers, George Michael Bedinger (1756-1843), Henry Bedinger II (1753-1843), and Daniel Bedinger (1761-1818), and their descendants and connections. Among the many subjects discussed are Indian warfare and conditions on the Virginia frontier; descriptions of the events of the Revolution; trading in salt and fur; experiences of Americans held prisoner by the British during the Revolution; flour milling in the Potomac valley; trade and transport of farm commodities; travel on the Mississippi to New Orleans, 1811-1812; James Rumsey and the development of the steamboat; the settling of Kentucky and Ohio, descriptions of Washington D.C., Philadelphia, and Baltimore at various times from 1800 to 1860; antebellum social life, South and North; and extensive comments on politics through 1860, particularly on the opposition to Federalism and the early Democratic-Republican Party.
Description taken from Guide to the Cataloged Collections in the Manuscript Department of the William R. Perkins Library, Duke University. (1980).
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Dandridge, Danske, 1858-1914
Bedinger, Daniel, 1761-1818
Bedinger family
Bedinger, Henry, 1812-1858
Bedinger, Serena Catherine
Bowne, Walter
Clay, Henry, 1777-1852
Cornwell family
Dandridge family
Lawrence family
Mitchell family
Southgate, Rufus King
Stephen, Adam
Washington family
Authors, American -- Correspondence
Horticultural writers -- United States
Diplomatic and consular service, American -- Denmark
Women authors -- United States
Denmark -- Foreign relations -- United States
United States -- Genealogy
Kentucky -- History -- Revolution, 1775-1783
West Virginia -- History -- 19th century
Shenandoah River Valley (Va. and W. Va.) -- History -- Revolution, 1775-1783
United States -- Foreign relations -- Denmark
United States -- History -- Revolution, 1775-1783
Photographs
Contents of Collection
- Correspondence Series, 1752-1950s and undated, (28 boxes)
  - Correspondence, 1752-1845 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1846-1849 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1850-1856 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, 1857-1862 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence, 1863-1875 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence, 1876-1882 (Box 6)
  - Correspondence, 1883-1885 (Box 7)
  - Correspondence, 1886-1887 (Box 8)
  - Correspondence, 1888-1889 (Box 9)
  - Correspondence, 1890-1891 (Box 10)
  - Correspondence, 1892-1894 (Box 11)
  - Correspondence, 1895-1896 (Box 12)
  - Correspondence, 1897-1899 (Box 13)
  - Correspondence, 1900-1901 (Box 14)
  - Correspondence, 1902-1903 (Box 15)
  - Correspondence, 1904-1905 (Box 16)
  - Correspondence, 1906-1907, Jan.-March (Box 17)
  - Correspondence, 1907, Apr.-Dec. (Box 18)
  - Correspondence, 1908 (Box 19)
  - Correspondence, 1909 (Box 20)
  - Correspondence, 1910 (Box 21)
  - Correspondence, 1911, Jan.-July (Box 22)
  - Correspondence, 1911, Aug.-1913 (Box 23)
  - Correspondence, 1914-1916 (Box 24)
  - Correspondence, 1917-1950s (Box 25)
  - Correspondence, undated (Box 26)
  - Correspondence, undated (Box 27)
  - Correspondence (copies), 1784-1854 (Box 28)
    Includes letters of Henry Bedinger II, Henry Bedinger Davenport, and Caroline (L.) Bedinger.
- Writings Series, (9 boxes)
  - Writings of Henry Bedinger III (Box 29)
    Copies of Bedinger papers in the Draper Collection, University of Wisconsin.
  - Writings of Danske Dandridge (Box 30)
    - Prose (Fiction)
    - St. Clair's Campaign (Box 31)
    - De Deah Old House
    - Heroes of the Vendee (Box 32)
    - Prose (Non-fiction)--including Garden Notes, 1899-1901 and letters about her garden to Lizette Reese (Box 33)
    - Cossack Celebration, poetry (Holo. MSS.), and prose (fiction) (Box 34)
    - Henry Bedinger and Old Shepherdstown (Box 35)
    - Henry Bedinger and Old Bedford
  - Writings of Serena C. (Violet) Dandridge (Box 36)
  - Elizabeth S. Pendleton, The Burning of Fountain Rock (Box 37)
  - Henrietta (Lee) Goldsborough, The Fate of Old Ironsides and Original Masts
  - Other writings by various people
- Miscellany Series, (8 boxes)
  - Legal Papers (Box 38)
  - Financial Papers
  - Financial Papers (Box 39)
  - Genealogy (Box 40)
  - Miscellany (Box 41)
  - Clippings (Box 42)
  - Printed Material: Leaflets, Broadsides, and pamphlets, 1827-1957 and undated (Box 43)
  - Photographs (Box 44)
  - Photographs (Box 45)
- Journals, Volumes, and Notebooks Series, (18 boxes)
  - Daniel Bedinger Journal, 1811-1812 (Box 46)
  - Hugh Stephenson, Muster Roll, 1776
  - Caroline (Lawrence) Bedinger, Letterbooks, 1848-1862
  - Mar (Bedinger) Mitchel, Memoirs, 1854-1860
  - Notebooks on family history: 1892; 1903; 1906; 1907; 1910
  - Danske Dandridge's Journals, 1864-ca. 1892 (Box 47)
  - Danske Dandridge's Journals, 1885-1904 (Box 48)
  - Danske Dandridge's journals, 1906-1909 (Box 49)
  - Danske Dandridge's Autobiography
  - Family record, 1877-1885
  - Poetry
  - Danske Dandridge's Garden notes, Journals, and articles (Box 50)
  - Notebooks for American Prisoners of the Revolution and Historic Shepherdstown (Box 51)
  - Notebooks for "Heroes of the Vendee" and "De Deah Old House" (Box 52)
  - Notebooks for "St. Clair's Campaign" (Box 53)
  - Writings of Danske Dandridge, including fiction and other prose (Box 54)
  - Serena Katherine (Violet) Dandridge poetry (Box 55)
  - Scrapbooks (Box 56)
  - Scrapbooks (Box 57)
  - Business Records (Box 58)
  - Business Records (Box 59)
  - Business Records (Box 60)
  - Miscellaneous Volumes (Box 61)
  - Miscellaneous Volumes (Box 62)
  - Miscellaneous Volumes (Box 63)
- Audiovisual materials, 2000, (1 item)
  - Immortal Essence: The Life and Writings of Danske Dandridge, Poet and Nature-Lover, shown on West Virginia Public Television., (VHS cassette) (Box 63)